Guide to the James J. Sheehan Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James J. Sheehan papers
1974-1999
1993-1997
SC1009
Sheehan, James J.
5.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
The materials were the gift of James Sheehan, 2010, 2011.
Information about Access
The materials are partially restricted. Accession 2011-204, Advisory Board materials (boxes 2-3), are restricted. See below for details.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commission on Undergraduate Education was created by Stanford University President Gerhard Casper in April 1993; it was charged with a comprehensive, year-long study of undergraduate education. James J. Sheehan, professor of history, was appointed its chair.
Scope and Contents note
The records include minutes, reports, correspondence, memoranda, press coverage, and background materials. Background materials of notes include press coverage on the CIV/Western Culture debate at Stanford, 1986-1990; and a report by James L. Gibbs, "Stanford Undergraduate Education in the Seventies: A Call for Educating the Whole Person" 1974.
Access Terms
Gibbs, James Lowell.; Sheehan, James J.; Stanford University. Commission on Undergraduate Education..; Education, Higher--Aims and objectives--California; Stanford University--Administration.; Stanford University--Faculty.; Universities and colleges--Administration.
Collection Contents
- Stanford University Commission on Undergraduate Education records, 1974-1995; Accession ARCH-2010-135
  - Commission, formation and charge, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees, 1993 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commission, statements by G. Casper, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Commission suggested membership (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Commission membership and C.V.'s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CUE membership, sub-committees (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commission, Faculty Senate, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CUE minutes, 1993 Oct.-Dec. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CUE minutes, 1994 Jan, March 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CUE minutes, 1994 Mar 25-Jun (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CUE Final Report, working draft, 1994 Jul 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Responses to final draft, 1994 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Final Report, language requirement (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Final Report, BR [Breadth Requirements] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Final Report, CIV (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Final Report, the major (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Final Report, grades, etc. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Final Report, calendar (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Final Report, technology (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Final Report, general advising (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Final Report, residential education (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Final Report, governance, etc. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Report of the Subcommittee on Academic Environment, 1994 June (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - BR [Breadth Requirements] Subcommittee, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report of the subcommittee on The Major, 1994 March (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Alumni response (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Center for Teaching and Learning (SU) publications (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - CIV/Western Culture debate, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - CIV/Western Culture debate, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CIV/Western Culture debate, press materials, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - CIV/Western Culture debate, coverage in Campus Report, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Studies, background materials, 1989-1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, etc., 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, etc., 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, etc., 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Course Enrollment data for 1988 Frosh cohort, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - CPPC [Career Planning and Placement Center] Survey Summaries: 1992-93 and 1993-94 academic years (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - CUE press coverage, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - CUE press coverage, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - CUE press coverage, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - CUE press coverage: original Stanford newspapers (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Focus Groups (DR [Distribution Requirements]), 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Focus groups (CIV/DR): Roz Pierson's raw data, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Gibbs, James L. "Stanford Undergraduate Education in the Seventies: A Call for Educating the Whole Person", 1974 May (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Haas Center for Public Services (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Irvine Foundation, clippings, reports, correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Light, Richard - visit to Stanford, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous materials (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mission statements of various universities (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mission statements, Stanford [unofficial], 1981, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - News Service digest on grading, 1994 July (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Political Correctness: a group research and policy recommendation project [student paper: no photocopy allowed], 1994 Winter (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Questions received for a possible CUE survey, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Reports, other universities, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Reports, other universities, 1988, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Senior Survey 1994, responses to open ended questions, unedited version (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Sheehan: Stanford Associates talk, 1993 Sep (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sheehan: Volunteers in Asia, re his talk to delegation from Japan Associaton of Private Colleges and Universities, 1993 Nov (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Source materials (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Source materials (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Source materials (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Stanford University Accreditation Self-Study, section on distribution requirements, 1001 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Stanford University Continuing Studies Program, A Perspective on the First Five Years, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Student Advisory Group. Report to the Commission on Undergraduate Education, [1994] (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Student Services and Undergraduate Education Survey Report, 1994 March (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Student Survey, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Committee Records, 1983-1999; Accession ARCH-2011-204
  Advisory Board materials are restricted. See below for details.
  - Lorez Eitner, "The Development of the Stanford Museum, 1964-1988" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Operating Budget Guidelines, 1992-1993 and Budget and Strategic Summary (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Accreditation, circa 1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Senate Committee on Education and Scholarship, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Senate Handbook, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Senate rosters and chairs, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Senate minutes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Steering Committee minutes, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hoover Committee, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - History Department minutes, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee on the professoriate, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hoover Resource Group Report, 1984 Jul (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Review of Modern Thought, Comparative Literature, Graduate Program in Humanities, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Reagan complex, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Task Force on Discipline, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stanford University Advisory Board (Box 2-3)
    - Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
      Restricted 20 years from date of creation.
    - Pfefferbaum case, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
      Restricted 75 years from date of creation.